One of my first jobs out of high school was working for a grocery store.
我在高中的时候给一家超市打工
It was a really interesting job.
这个工作很有意思
I got to meet a lot of people,
每天都遇见很多不一样的人
and I also got to observe all of the interesting ways that a grocery store works.
我也可以观察到关于超市运营的一些很有意思的点
Now, picture grocery store with me.
现在 请跟我一起 想象一家超市
You walk in, and the store is stocked,
走进超市 满满的货架
you'll have everything from vegetables,
蔬菜、
all the way to canned goods,
罐头
and there are all of these different products.
应有尽有
Followed behind that, you have people that come into the store,
然后想象顾客走进超市
and every person is going to have different behaviors.
每个顾客行为都是不一样的
Some are coming in for one specific item,
有些已经知道自己要买什么了
others are coming in and they're browsing the store.
有些只是先进来逛逛
Now, at the end of that browsing period,
逛完结束后
the customer is going to come check out,
顾客要结算
they're going to pay for whatever they've bought, and they're going to leave.
付完钱后他们就走了
Now, imagine trying to grow this grocery store without any data.
试问 如果没有数据 这个超市该如何提升它的经营？
We couldn't, we'd have no idea what to put on the shelf,
没有数据 我们就无法知道在货架上摆哪些产品
or how much we can pay our employees,
给员工开多少工资
or whether we were making any money at all.
甚至不知道我们是否盈利
So think about owning a grocery store.
所以 以超市为例
What data would we want to collect?
我们应该收集哪些数据呢？
Well, if we take a top-down approach,
如果是 top-down (由上至下) 的方式
let's think about our objectives.
我们先要想清楚目标
Primarily, we need to sell groceries,
在这个例子里 目标当然是要盈利
and we need to be profitable.
也要提高销量
So if we need to be profitable,
所以如果要确保盈利
then we need to make sure that we're capturing data on sales,
首先要确保我们有每个月的销量数据
and we also need to have data on how much we're spending,
支出和成本数据
and how much we're making money.
以及盈利多少
If we need to sell groceries,
如果是要提高销量
then we need to keep track of what products we're moving.
我们需要知道哪些产品卖得好
Now, from a bottom-up approach,
如果是 bottom-up （由下至上）方法
we could ask this a different way.
就不同了
What if instead we wanted to answer the question,
比如 我们想了解这些情况
what are the most popular hours at my grocery store?
超市最火爆的时段是哪些？
Well, what data do you think we would need to answer this question?
为了回答这个问题 你觉得需要什么数据呢？
Well, I would need to measure how many people come to the store each hour.
首先 需要知道每个时段都有多少人进入超市
But here's the tricky part. How do we quantify what we mean by popular?
但是遇到个问题 怎么来定义“火爆”呢？
Is the store popular because there are lots of people in it for that hour?
火爆是指人最多的时候吗？
Or is the store popular because we make the most money in that hour?
还是指营业额最高的时候呢？
Well, that's going to depend on your business objectives.
这就要看你的业务目标了
If you opened up a brand new grocery store,
如果你新开一家超市
you might be focusing on awareness,
认知度可能是你的首要目标
you simply want foot traffic.
你目前只需要更多的人流
Therefore, you might want to measure how many people are
所以 在考虑盈利问题前 你可以先考虑
coming through the store more than you care about whether you're making money yet.
每个时段进来的人数
Now, a more mature grocery store might be
一家更为成熟的超市则可能更关心盈利问题
concerned about making money during a certain period of time,
某个时段的
and therefore, popularity would be a measurement of revenue during that timeframe.
所以可能会选择盈利的多少来作为“火爆”的判断标准
Now, the point of this thought experience is to get you to
这个小小的思考过程是帮助你开始思考
start thinking about all of the nuances in the marketing analytics process.
市场分析过程里涉及到的很多类似的问题
We need to know what questions we want to answer,
我们需要知道要去问哪些问题
and then we need to know how we will qualify that that's the answer we want.
然后再去像该怎么判断我们的答案可以合格地回答这些问题
From there, we can figure out the right data to combine.
然后 我们去找合适的数据来分析
When it comes to answering questions,
要回答问题
we're always combining data.
肯定需要整合数据
Let's think about a few more questions we can ask in regards to our grocery store.
再来几道超市的情景问题吧
Some will be easy to qualify.
有一些会比较容易判断
What isn't selling?
什么产品卖得不好？
So we can simply measure what products sold and which products didn't,
我们只需要知道产品销量就可以知道哪些卖得好、卖得不好
there isn't a lot of data to combine there.
不需要整合太多数据
What about how many repeat customers do we get?
下一个问题 我们有多少回头客？
So that's a measurement of loyalty,
这是衡量顾客的忠诚度
although we're simply asking how many times a customer comes during a period of time.
我们可以考虑一个客户在固定的一段时间内来多少次
How about where is most of our profit coming from?
再来一道 我们的盈利来源于哪里？
Probably easy to qualify as well,
也不太难
maybe do we ever run out of stock,
再比如 我们是否有库存不够的情况？
if so, on what or how much money would we lose on a particular day?
如果有 那么将一天损失多少钱？
But some questions are harder to qualify.
有些问题就比较难回答
Take this one. Are customers loyal?
比如这个 你的顾客是否忠诚？
Well, what does loyalty mean?
那么 如何定义忠诚呢？
Is loyalty a measurement of how much money someone spends?
是指某个顾客消费的额度吗？
Is loyalty a measurement of how many times they visit?
还是他们的消费次数呢？
Is loyalty a measure of how many times they visit in a period of time?
还是在某段时间的消费次数呢？
Is it three times a week or three times a year?
每周三次为准？每年三次为准？
That's for you to decide.
这就要你来决定了
Another really tough question to qualify,
另一个很难回答的问题是
is the store laid out in a good manner?
超市布局合理吗？
Well, that's another tough one,
这个真的很难回答
because we have to combine all sorts of data.
因为我们要整合很多不同的数据
Is the store laid out in a good manner depends on our goals.
首先 判断是否合理要看我们的业务目标
Are we trying to sell a particular product?
我们是想要卖出某个特定的产品吗？
Perhaps we're pushing a new product,
可能超市在推某个产品
therefore we might decide that it needs to be on an end cap,
所以我们决定放在了某列货架的开头
and we decide that if it sells more than if it was in a row,
如果比在货架中间部分卖得好
then yes, the store was laid out better than if it was put somewhere else.
那么 布局是合理的
There are all sorts of metrics that have to be layered into that.
在回答问题时 需要考虑各种指标
Ultimately, what we're trying to accomplish is
最终 我们要达成的目标是
becoming aware of how we have to frame our mindset.
了解自己如何分析问题
Every time we think of questions to answer,
每次试图回答某个问题时
we must also be aware of how we're qualifying whether we've arrived at the right answer.
我们需要考虑判断问题答案的标准是否合理